welcome to the Hard Day's Medicine
inspirations podcast with Professor dr.
yang Bolivar and Daniel SHM Acton Berger
Thank You Daniel thank you for being
with us today thanks for putting this
together we had a chance today to talk
about harvest medicine during the board
meeting and during the opening ceremony
and just wondering what does heart based
medicine look like for you if you were
describe it in your own hands
and the first
in a sense that I have is that people
are called to a life path in the healing
professions because of a care for the
quality of experience of other people
and the actual sacredness of human life
and human experience and wanting to be
in service to and devotion to that so
heart based medicine would be with the
entire system of medicine and all of the
interactions were designed from and in
service to that devotion in that
sacredness so heart based medicine is
about a sacred space for you yeah I mean
we think about medicine being preventing
and correcting illness and promoting
health people's experience of life and
what they can do with their life to
affect the experience of others is
sacred
so then medicine is what is in service
to their capacity to experience life
fully and contributes life fully in many
ways this is where medicine is coming
from at least in our part of the world
in our culture's that medicine was very
much in the domain of the religious
missions and that was the understanding
of healthcare that was the understanding
of care given and of elevating the
potential of the ones we serve yeah is
this something very specific to to our
culture's most is something that you see
as a she like as a principle beyond the
kind of cultural and religious
background Center we share Emerson here
I think this might be as unifying a
thing across cultures as there is in
terms of medicine women and medicine men
and shamans and Chinese medicine and
Ayurvedic medicine like early humans
figuring out how do we care for each
other how do we care for ourselves how
do we
prevent illness how do we fix illness
obviously the whole focus to do that
would be not just self-preservation but
also care for each other so I think
that's probably as unifying a thing as
there is yeah so care is the unifying
principle
so if care is the unifying principle and
we see that all the talk in healthcare
about the importance of care and we see
how it is delivered what do you see as
the current the strongest obstacles
those those elements in our current
healthcare system in the way that we
feel about healthcare what do you see as
the trying obstacles to deliver the kind
of care that we would perceive as a
secret mm-hmm a lot actually and I'm I'm
happy to unpack this but there's a lot
of systemic factors there's obviously
trillions of dollars flowing through the
thing we call global healthcare
industrial complex writ large and
pharmaceuticals and hospitals and
industries and insurance industries
there's also all of the money in the
world flowing through things that affect
health when we look at the burning of
coal and oil and what that does to the
environment that then we're embedded in
and breathing and drinking the water
from when we look at agriculture that
depletes the topsoil or sprays
glyphosate on all the food like upstream
from someone being sick and coming to
the hospital as do we actually have a
civilization that's promoting health and
in how many places do we have a
civilization that through structures
that creative liquidus psychological
stress and structures that actually
again expose us to the liquidus
pollution and poor forms of nutrition
when you just think about it like the
goal of almost
every business is to maximize the
lifetime revenue of a customer and
nothing does that better than addiction
obviously the the supply side might be a
multi-billion dollar company relative to
an individual consumer and so there's a
kind of asymmetric warfare in terms of
their capacity to influence with
commercial media you know so many things
so if we wanted a society that was
promoting maximum health we would want
to be minimizing addiction everywhere
which would mean that any place where
addiction was profitable we would have a
fundamental conflict we'd have a
perverse incentive in the nature of that
type of market dynamic so you know I
think there's a huge amount of perverse
incentive that's one place where there
are structural issues I think that there
are places where out of caution because
of malpractice and whatever else
hospitals create policies there are
insurance guidelines that actually don't
allow doctors to do things that would
demonstrate certain kinds of care I
think that we have a medical school
system where the average amount of
nutrition that is taught to a medical
doctor is extraordinarily low relative
to the importance of nutrition and
health but similarly how much psychology
should actually be taught so that the
doctor can actually really understand
the experience of the patient well and
be able to relate and work through that
should be a much bigger percentage of
the training that occurs I think we also
have a situation where you can't
actually measure the felt sense of love
and care in the same way that you can
measure cholesterol and blood pressure
and so you end up optimizing for the
things that you measure
I think MRI machines are expensive and
they're important so you make big
hospitals that a lot of people go to as
opposed to small County clinics and
because there's economies of scale but I
think the economies of scale mean you
don't really know your doctor your
doctor doesn't know you
you're one of maybe hundreds or
thousands of people that they're going
to see and so I think again the
economies of scale end up really
damaging personal connection and
personal rapport I think the most
important diagnostic tool there is is
really detailed medical intake and
really having the time to think through
and pay attention and then a continuity
of being able to think about that for
the patient and there's just that
requires a certain amount of time being
allocated so I think there's a lot of
structural factors that are oriented to
things like lowering liability and
maximizing profit and economies of scale
all of which are not optimized for what
supposedly the whole thing isn't
serviced - mmm thank you that makes a
lot of sense resonate very much with the
importance of intake that is based on a
deep listening really being present as
the patient understanding where they're
coming from and seeing that disease
through their eyes where you're talking
about you're touching on many issues but
you are also touching on one of the
points you are raising is that the
person's subjective experience of their
disease and how they feel and what it
means to their lives is something that
is worth exploring and yet it is hard to
measure so the measures that we
currently have available are I think too
crude or are they just is it just
structurally impossible to measure the
subjective experience
well bye-bye definition it is
structurally impossible to measure
subjective experience a measurement
means some needle move means it's in the
domain of the object or third person I
can measure a neural correlate I can
measure a endocrine correlate otherwise
I have to actually listen to the person
report their own experience then of
course we're gonna have all the biases
that self reporting has and someone
having reasons they don't want to say
how miserable they are or they want to
exaggerate it for empathy or they have a
limited vocabulary to express it so I do
think that there is a need for a lot of
question asking of things that cannot be
measured in blood tests so how do we
deal with this approach so we we know
that when we talk to patients that we
find out things and as you say there are
biases so there's the preferences
there's recall there is you know there's
all sorts of things that that affect
this and and a lot of the approaches
that we take in in everyday routine
clinics is trying to bring some insert
some objectivity into this assessment
seeing to what degree can we rely on
this but in a way what we do is we take
our tests that we apply our observations
of that person that we call objective
observations we take those as the
reference point and whatever the patient
says is measured against that yeah when
I kill you correctly then what we really
want to do is we want to improve on
understanding the subjective experience
better
okay so there's there's a number of
parts we can look at here there's the
way that someone's subjective experience
affects their objective physiology right
- the whole domain of
psychoneuroimmunology and the way that
stress affects health and the way that
better psychological disposition placebo
dynamics etc affect health so we want to
actually be able to work with people
subjective experience as part of
medicine that's one thing the other
thing is that some people might have a
disease that can't be cured and actually
still have a good subjective experience
of life based on their focus and their
meaning making versus having a totally
ruined experience of life so subjective
experience is a terminal value in and of
itself it so it is both useful for
supporting objective physiologic health
and it is intrinsically valuable
independent of physiologic health
there's a bunch of other reasons to talk
for patient and ask them questions
though you and I were talking before
that modern allopathic medicine does a
really good job in places where we
actually understand the causation
clearly and generally that tends to be
more in the direction of things that
were acute like an acute injury it's
pretty clear like oh there was a
puncture wound we're gonna sew up the
puncture wound or there was an acute
infection and we can see what type of
infection it is maybe an antibiotic can
treat it or there was a acute poisoning
and we're gonna do in a huge kind of
detox but there was a acute incident and
then immediate symptom ology and we can
trace causation but with autoimmune
disease and with cognitive decline and
neurodegenerative disease and
psychiatric disease and cancer that's
not the case and so for the most part we
don't actually know why those things are
happening and it happens to be my belief
similar to much of the kind of
functional medicine and naturopathic
world that most of those diseases are
multifactorial they don't have one cause
they have a lot of causes and it's not
the same set of causes every time so
there actually isn't one thing called
rheumatoid arthritis or one thing called
MS from a path audiology point of view
there's a system that's being exposed to
things that don't create immediate
symptom ology but that are dis
regulating homeo dynamics and those
dysregulated homeo dynamics make one
more susceptible to the additional
stressors dis regulating homeo dynamics
more until eventually we caught cross a
threshold and now we get
symptom ology and biomarkers and a
cluster of symptoms II and biomarkers
gets a disease name and but if I really
start paying attention to those things
and wanting to be able to trace a
complex causal situation that's
multifactorial and maybe very delayed
causation and time then I want a totally
different kind of intake right I might
want to be asking really detailed
questions to see when they've ever been
exposed to mold when they were ever
exposed to industrial chemicals or they
spend a lot of time with epoxy at a
certain point or whatever it is or when
they had third world travels where they
got nasty infections and what symptoms
so I want a timeline of when different
symptoms kicked on and a timeline of
different kinds of stresses and
exposures when there was a micro
traumatic brain injury that didn't show
up in an MRI but it doesn't mean that
there actually wasn't a micro TBI that
affected functional patterning in the
brain and if I'm able to look at the
current symptomology the current labs
the progression of symptoms and the
progression of exposures and have all of
that fit together and make sense and I
might be informed as to how to start a
treatment that is actually addressing
more than just symptom ology and you
know disease manifestation mm-hmm and
there's no one going to get that without
asking them a lot of questions yeah so
is there you do you feel that this is
this is an area of research that is
developing I mean I I think that the
environmental medicine functional
medicine and naturopathic medicine
communities have been focused on with
chronic complex illness in particular
where that best modern treatments are
mostly symptomatic you know and not just
symptomatic or biologic can actually
decrease the total tissue damage from a
connective tissue disorder and obviously
if we're cutting a cancer out or
radiating it out or poisoning it out
that's still better than leaving it
there often times but why was there
increased cars
Genesis in the first place and why did
the body's immune system not deal with
the carcinogenesis are still applying
questions especially if we don't want
this person to get cancer again and
especially if the things that might have
led to it might be signs of underlying
dysregulation that affect other things
so I think there is a increasing
awareness that chronic complex illness
is not just stupid bodies it is just
kind of deeper complexity where it's not
one disease one cause and we're gonna
have one pill it is radically complex
regulatory systems many different
elements of causation that end up
leading to things that present like a
cluster of symptoms and biomarkers we
call it disease and it's very
fascinating is it I think in most of the
research that received published today
most of the clinical researchers means
maybe see published today what I observe
is that they skim attic the methodology
is very much the same so we kind of have
two up two points of observation and
between the two points of observation we
assume a linear correlation but we don't
look at our Q if you look at the classic
table one in a publication where we were
looking at the demographics comparing
the two groups you know three or four or
five different variables so we're
looking at you know its gender ethnicity
age so really really crude variables and
at the end everybody feels comfortable
that both groups are comparable while
we're not looking at it so it's what
happens before the trial
what are these life stories well as this
what is this
the complex of Romeo dynamic regulatory
systems interacting with each other and
building up in a way that that we have
great difficulties to establish we
certainly don't have any measures or
markers for this when we establish these
let's say if we get better at asking
questions and really getting at least a
reporting picture of what happened do
you feel that the if we basically
exploded the number of variables from
you know age and sex and ethnicity to
two maybe let's say 200 or 500 variables
so if we were compiling this index of
measures or indicators would we really
learn more about what happened before an
event yeah so
what are the right methods to gain the
kinds of insights we want and domain as
complex as human physiology is a very
interesting question if we look at a
clinical trial say for drug research
it's trying to see does this drug do
something beyond the placebo we're gonna
get something like a Gaussian
distribution where all we you know it's
gonna work pretty well for some people
and it's gonna work not well for other
people and there will be some range of
effect for a lot of people we just want
to see that that's some range of effect
and maybe the front of the bell curve is
better than what a placebo is but why it
works really well for these people and
not really well for these people or
maybe even really badly for these people
is a bunch of other variables that are
just hidden under the shape of a bell
curve and so obviously we would like to
find that out so that doesn't mean that
that is a worthless study that's an
interesting study that it if we go all
the way to the other end we get how can
we get as much information about this
one person as possible rather than this
one drug across all people right how can
give as much information about this
person and now we're starting to do N
equals one kinds of studies and
optimization so I totally think there
are places for clinical trials of course
if we have more metrics if they're
appropriate metrics additional insight
comes because it's not just are you
likely to be able to see more things but
you also start to get to see what are
the relationships between these metrics
and are there combinatorial insights but
as soon as I realize that I'm not just
looking at a genome I'm looking at the
combinatorics on all of the
polymorphisms possible on all of the the
genes and then all the combinatorics on
the epigenome and then the proteome
recursively changing it we're never
going to be able to compute all that it
is actually not computable so there are
better ways we have to think about how
do we actually understand what health is
and if we think about hope health has
the integrity of the regulatory system
so the homeo dynamics of how the body
self organizes and self-regulates and
the homeo dynamic not just the homeo
dynamic state the Tomeo dynamic capacity
I'd like typically most of the studies
that most of tests we do in medicine are
testing state so we're testing
cholesterol level or we're testing blood
sugar or whatever it is but what's
really going to determine the overall
health is much more related to under
some kind of stress how does the body
maintain being within homeo dynamic
range so you know we do this sometimes
with a glucose stress test or with a
stress echo cardiogram and those are
super insightful but there's a lot of
things we don't do those with work it
might be in range but very fragile and
could come out of range easily which
means that the person doesn't have a
disease but they're very susceptible and
so yet if I see very high homeo dynamic
capacity across lots of axes that's a
measure of the robustness of health so
you know different types of interesting
diagnostics in the future so we are so
what I hear from you is assuming linear
you need causal association is as a
degree of simplification that silly is
really not very helpful maybe for some
things in the knife wound case it's fine
yeah except we need to ask you know are
they clumsy or are they getting in knife
fights for dumb reason so there might be
something upstream but so for some
things you need causal is fine but for
most anything that emerged not
immediately following an obvious
causation event this is why we don't
actually have real cures we have
symptomatic treatments and you know
ameliorative treatments for most complex
chronic disease so the etiology of
disease we will more likely find answers
for what is the real cause of disease if
we look at our models and we look at the
the period before that this is started
before the symptoms of her and see what
what are the different factors that have
built up and reached that threshold yeah
when you speculate about what might be
their areas
that effect the human body what are the
areas that if they stuck up will lead to
an imbalance of dysregulation that
becomes symptomatic yeah you know
there's some actual pretty simple models
we can start to look at this
comprehensively through so I mean
Chinese medicine and Ayurvedic medicine
actually had some kind of good holistic
sure it's thickest to start with even
though they didn't have all the
assessments we have like say you take a
roughly Chinese medicine point of view
of where is there too much of something
where is there not enough of something
so toxicity and deficiency this is
pretty good starting model for
predispositions towards disease so you
can think about that we evolved to be
able to like our genetics evolved to
have a certain set of behaviors
interacting with a certain set of
environmental parameters so where our
behaviors are very different then kind
of what we evolved to handle or where
our environment is meaningfully
different those are going to be
interesting things to look at so you
know too much well too much can look
like things that we shouldn't have any
amount of like glyphosate and pesticides
and you know and we're really kind of
Ubiquiti sley exposed to the volatile
organic compounds coming out of this
carpet and out of the panes right this
we have built a world that we're
actually not genetically fit for where
there are externalities to our health of
the ways that we do lots of things and
so when you look at all the volatile
organic compounds or all of the you know
petrochemicals that are in the
environment most of them are either
endocrine disruptors or neurotoxins or
percentage ins so then we look at how
many diseases fit into those being part
of the underlying ideology think so too
much things that shouldn't have really
been there at all
and but obviously too much sugar or you
know the there can be excesses of
certain nutrients in relationship to
other nutrients like zinc copper balance
or calcium magnesium balance or things
like that obviously we're not just
limited to talking about environmental
toxins that aren't alive we can also
talk about things that are alive so
infection would be kind of a subclass of
too much of something and that can
either be things that should be there
but they're overgrown like SIBO and
other kinds of microbiome disorders or
actual infections but pathogens that are
not normally part of our healthy kind of
microbiome and this is where the concept
of a subclinical infection or a
subclinical toxicity is important which
is let's say that I have a level of
mercury exposure or a level of lead
exposure where we're gonna say oh yes I
have lead poisoning
well lead poisoning is at this threshold
but the ideal amount of lead that I
would have would be down here well
there's a whole level in here which is I
don't yet have the level that we were
diagnosed with acute lead poisoning that
is more than none it has some effect and
that also ends up being true with
infections that are not necessarily
showing up as a cute infection but are
testable and that have effect so we see
Helicobacter pylori in the stomach being
able to cause ulcers and cause stomach
cancer over a very long time period or H
P V and cervical cancer or throat cancer
things like that for those few that
we've found recently it's pretty safe to
assume that there's a lot more like that
where the correlations are just not as
clear yet and that's one of the things
that again some of the infectious study
and environmental toxicology studies
that functional medicine is doing I
think are really interesting so too much
of various things not enough of and
obviously we can look at things like not
enough exercise not enough sleep not
enough
human contact the amount of human
contact is actually profound because
that ends up being one of the most
profound drivers of addiction which is
then gonna cause so many other health
issues but also not enough of specific
nutrients and we see that we have a you
know modern American diet or modern
industrial world diet it's very high in
macronutrients and often low in really
critical micronutrients and longevity is
usually best optimized by lower
macronutrients and higher micronutrients
which is closer to what evolutionary
environments would have so that's like a
studying framework mmm thank you so here
you have identified areas of risk
factors and if they're compiling they
might add so these are the areas that we
would like to explore further and more
deeply in in an intake as you described
it where we asked lots of questions and
trying to understand what happened
before that the patient has reached a
stage of disease yeah when we don't have
a lot of time than talking to the
patient's when you mentioned the
systemic factors the limiting factors of
how we are setting up our healthcare
system certainly I I feel that limited
time is a critical factor we need to
make choices
we need to make choices about what
questions to ask and one way is to go
through a protocol one way is to go
through a long list of questions and ask
for all the possible questions and then
I hope that either ourselves or some
computer will be able to
sensitive and then there's another way
to make choices and that depends it
involves the observer so it involves the
way we show up as a health care provider
who relate to the patient and we ask
these questions he briefly touched on
the subjective experience of the disease
and you talk you've touched on homeo
dynamics as as the cue principle to
understand behind disease evolution now
if we see that you're a home a dynamic
system and I'm a home here than any 16
is there a way that those two systems
can come into resonance is there a way
that I can tune my system into yours and
by doing so I can actually ask the right
questions I wouldn't ask you as a
clinician have you had this experience
yeah that's what it seems like
I don't think we have to get hung up on
wondering what the mechanism of
intuition is to acknowledge that there's
a reality to it is it some
electromagnetic resonance that's
happening maybe this cool idea is it
simply that I have a lot of experience
and when I take the time to quiet I
process the information in my own
internal neurologic database better
that's a fine idea too
I don't really I don't actually don't
want to attached to a mechanistic
explanation of how intuition works that
someone can say not well enough verified
and reject to say the increasing
awareness and presence and perceptive
'ti is valuable and it will lead to
better insights from wherever that comes
about what's going on with the patient
and how to ask the right questions
that's interesting so you're leaving
care as a sacred space and you're
viewing intuition as a sacred space so
it feels like we need to talk about love
in a way connecting the two at least
that's what it feels like to me
here's another sacred space and another
question now can we measure or should we
measure what might be the value of
measuring how we relate and and how we
describe the phenomenon of
we talked about this earlier we can't
measure love we can measure things going
on with the physiology when we say that
we're feeling something that we call
love
it may be statistically correlated to
some degree and whether I'm measuring
oxytocin and other kind of neural
hormones and neurotransmitters or I'm
measuring heart rate variability or
measuring some kind of EEG coherence
pattern those aren't useless things to
do like that's interesting but I could
just say pick the right person to marry
on paper whether you have any things for
them or not and just snort oxytocin
regularly because love is just oxytocin
and most people don't resonate with that
or or you know do a particular kind of
transcranial magnetic stimulation to the
brain region that we identified is where
love is happening and there it is when a
parent wakes up who is sick and who
hasn't slept in a long time who has an
infant who's worn out as can be to take
care of their infant love is motivating
them but they might feel like in
the moment and love doesn't really feel
like a subjective emotion it's actually
something deeper than emotion it's
transcendent to emotion it can move them
even through emotion and we might not
see a look up you know the particular
great heart rate variability in that
moment or whatever it is so I think it's
interesting to study correlation between
physiology and subjective states but I
think if we're studying it through the
method of science and we can do a lot
more with the objective within the
method of science because that's what we
study things that are measurable and
repeatable and experience objective
experience is not immeasurable nor were
people then the temptation is going to
be to reduce subjectivity to being an
Epiphone
the objectivity and in doing so then
consciousness is illusory and choice is
illusory or their consciousness is real
as an epiphenomena but choice is
illusory because everything that happens
in the brain is controlled by particle
physics of the voltage differentials or
sodium ions that's the exact opposite of
heart based anything faint like that is
kind of maximum reductionism and it's
not even epistemic ly well-founded it's
a category error of seeing that there is
some pretty low degree of information
theoretic correlation between objective
and subjective pretending that it's
perfect and then pretending that this is
the epiphenomena of this one because
this is the one that we know how to
actually make causal sense of do I think
it's important to have some way of
noticing how the doctor and how the
nurse and how the practitioners feel
before they're with patients and they're
paying attention to how the patients are
feeling and they're paying attention to
the quality of the relationship totally
I don't think you can measure that I
think you can pay attention to it I
think that you may have some indices
that are worth noticing but there will
be meaningful things that can't be
brought into an index and the moment you
do you're actually collapsing something
very information-rich to something very
not information rich and you're losing
so much information in the process that
if if you make your decisions as a
hospital or an insurance company or a
doctor based off the thing that lost all
the information and then you normalize
this is the thing we want to do we mess
it up it's beautiful so so basically our
our attempt to simplify questions so
that we feel comfortable to answer them
so this reductionist approach limits our
ability to see just by the by the fact
that we're setting targets to see
yeah that the hell that is nameable is
not the eternal towel so ultimately good
medicine is not purely algorithmic and
our job is not just to try and be robots
that just get data that we just haven't
got good enough robots to do yet but
will be replaced by them and then do if
this then that
programs it's actually not that that's
not the job that's a part of the job but
that's definitely not the whole totality
the job so there is something to what
medicine is it is trans algorithmic and
so then you have to say well if we're
gonna be training doctors and if we're
gonna be evaluating them based on a set
of metrics and a scorecard so then they
are gonna try and perform to the
scorecard they're gonna mess up the
actual thing this is what the note this
is how I interpret with the no false
idols thing is about right is that that
that kind of graven image of that set of
metrics isn't actually the thing it was
pointing at it's not worthless to pay
attention to those things but you
actually have to have your choice making
be bound to the actual reality not the
information reduced model it's very
interesting particularly when we think
of artificial intelligence entering the
space of Medicine so when we look at now
there are computers being built that
exhibiting some features that we would
describe as compassionate for example
non-judgmental listening so some of the
robots are now able to listen to a human
being and
in a way that they there is a feedback
to the one that that is that that is
talking but it's non-judgmental this
this is there's a conflation of ideas in
here to say non-judgmental assumes a
binary with judgmental that word right
we're correlating our experience of a
human that is judgmental or
non-judgmental that computer is not
being non-judgmental nor judgmental
there's actually no one home there is no
quality it is doing an if this than that
kind of program and even if it's doing a
deep learning program it is simply a
fully causal input-output through some
set of program dynamic so it's not
really fair to call that non judgmental
it is doing a function it's doing what
it's told
and the interesting observation is is
that when people with certain disease
conditions are interacting with these
computers there seems to be a level of
trust or acceptance that evolves and
that those patients exhibiting features
that we would describe as autistic to
the spectrum will reduce and they will
be able to open up and actually start a
conversation I think that that is a
statement of how shitty the parenting is
and how shitty the doctors nurses and
educators are that the person does
better the robot like a fairly low level
robot rather than it is something
exciting about AI for me if someone's
doing better with a robot because it
simply doesn't seem judgmental and it
takes a little space even though it
doesn't love you or care about you like
that's just a really low bar I'd rather
the person have a dog it's just been
time with the thing I'm excited about
with AI and the medicine space and it's
it's confusing to even call the a
machine learning do we want to have
machine learning run big datasets to
find correlations that we can't
currently find of course that's awesome
do we wanna like scan all the medical in
you know medical records in using image
recognition and run massive big data so
that we can see early disease indicators
we don't currently know that's awesome
and so far has an and of course we
should be augmenting just like we
augment human memory with books and
computers we should augment human
computational process this computational
process so the ability to take a picture
of something and have image recognition
be able to do better diagnosis of skin
can is like all of that's great and that
actually allows as that gets better it
allows the doctors to be less focused on
just memory and computation and more
focused on actual connection to them
know how to use that system and to
relate to the person but they're still
going to be a pretty big gap between the
doctor relating with the person using
the system and the system acting on the
person directly so you know the
availability and we can run this on
databases as you say but we can also
turn them into wiki we can inform
objects that we call robots with machine
learning abilities so they are able to
provide services so what we're seeing is
that increasingly now there are kind of
robots evolving that are involved and
what we typically would cause call
services of care so for example they
would help in in household activity
helping you know basic getting dressed
washing ourselves very basic day-to-day
activities and they are helpful for
people who have incapacity you know
somehow they don't have the capacity to
perform certain activities now but
they're fundamentally different to a
nurse coming to the home an extra being
with this person and providing that
support yeah there's something about the
development of these technologies that
is awesome and liberating and helpful
and there's something about the way we
are relating to it it is gruesome and
it's important to understand both
insofar as we're talking about a robotic
exoskeleton that can allow a paralyzed
person to walk it's just a better
wheelchair like me it's just an
extension of the tool thing we've
already been using you're wearing
eyeglasses that's a tool that helps you
you're a cyborg to some degree if we had
ones that could autofocus and do cool
stuff like okay that's fine
but something that does not actually
have the capacity to care about you
replacing a dynamic where care used to
occur is tragic now if it's simply
helping you get some stuff done you
couldn't otherwise and hopefully that
increases your capacity for authentic
human interaction awesome that the
tendency of hyper individualization that
the modern world has had modern West in
particular has had every time you see a
mass shooter who should took a bunch of
people at school or somewhere almost all
the time when the news goes and checks
the neighbors say yeah he was super
quiet he kept to himself nobody ever saw
him because in a setting where you have
a family or an extended family or a
village where humans evolved for most of
human history if your before you would
go kill a bunch of people you're
obviously not happy
and if you're interacting with other
people to get your needs met that people
see that they'll actually be responding
and keeping that psychopathology from
progressing that far but if someone can
be a shut-in and they can hardly ever
interact with anyone then maybe get an
Amazon drone delivery to their house so
they actually never have to interact
with anyone now they can have some
robotic care agents they can progress in
psychopathology both in ways that make
them dangerous to society and in ways to
just allow them to be suffering
gruesomely for a long time humans are
social primates we evolved in social
environments we have a world that
totally is getting this wrong right now
and we we have to turn that thing around
for they're not just to like have an
optimal world I actually don't think we
have any chance of having a world to
continue at all from the point of view
of existential catastrophic risk if we
don't solve this particular thing
because say someone is progressing in
psychopathology and they're really upset
and the best technology for killing they
have is a knife they're just not gonna
hurt that many people before somebody
takes them out but if it's an ar-15 they
can kill a lot more people with
decentralizing exponential technology
when that becomes a CRISPR gene Drive
pandemic weapon and weaponized drones
and etc we just can't have really
disaffected people and that means if I
can get all of my needs met without
interacting with other humans then
either I have to have some top-down
state surveillance system like the China
method which is already a dystopia or
how do we have access to the level of
technological power people be giving and
have us be safe vessels for having that
much technological power well they have
to be know psychologically really
damaged people and if there are any we
have to know the only way to have that
kind of known that doesn't involve
top-down state surveillance is the kind
of surveillance that a family does or a
tribe does or a community does where my
resource provisioning
fires interacting in healthy ways where
people were unlike the kind of
asymmetric surveillance of the state
that is just trying to make sure I'm not
a bad guy it's a symmetric paying
attention of people that actually want
to make sure I'm doing well so part of
the what you're proposing is a community
civilian no way so are you saying
basically that doesn't even have to be
the death because it's it's an innate
function of building primary communities
that we are resonating with each other
and that we're realizing if somebody is
behaving kind of outside of the pact
then then that is something to be
addressed and would you argue that this
is something that is a it's like an
existential interest of the group of
quarters of the potential so is this
like a risk detection system of the
group does this mean that nobody can be
a hermit no of course it doesn't mean
nobody can be a hermit but it doesn't
mean that in the presence of
decentralized able catastrophe level
technology we have to think about some
things differently than we did
previously and the disposition and
well-being of people matters more to
everyone because the one-to-many
capacity of a person is much much higher
and so the coupling is higher which
means that the care needs behind coming
back to care again and again and again
so now we're looking at care is a group
phenomena so a group caring for the
group and caring for individuals for the
sake of the group and for this they
could be individual and for the sake of
the individual so if I'm just
translating this to the healthcare
setting though where we have a group of
people working together and we have
individuals walking in and out of this
setting and we look at the current I
want to call it academic of suicides
[Music]
where we're failing is it have we become
them has the system numbed ourselves
have we lost a sensitivity you're
specifically talking about suicide
amongst doctors I don't know I haven't
studied this I would want to really look
at is suicide much higher amongst
doctors than other professionals of the
same pay grades and other types of
similar stress level like I'm sure again
there's gonna be complex causation
that's involved it's not one thing we
can talk about why there are kind of
epidemic suicide issues society-wide
but yeah I wouldn't want to speak to
with doctors without knowing more but I
think it's pretty easy to see at least
some things I think it's pretty easy to
see that the amount of stress doctors go
through even in med school I
experiencing burnout or being on some
kind of wellbutrin or adderall or
Ritalin or some kind of upper just to
make it through in school by the time
they're just not even graduating and
then they're supposed to have a whole
career then like you mentioned 72 hour
shifts and I also think that not having
a place to process the emotionality of
it the desensitization of okay so I just
you know as a part of some kids dying
today this experience and I'm gonna go
do it tomorrow and where's the space for
that and yeah I think I think there's
obviously a lot of stresses both that
are unavoidably endemic to that
profession that need to be processed in
ways that they aren't currently
processed and ones that are avoidable by
changing the way the system works
so we could as a group become all
proficient in detecting the dynamics of
the group and taking care of each other
and we could become more proficient in
the way that we show up as an individual
in the group and that's showing up more
proficient with our peer group with our
teams and with the patient will help us
to see the patient better see our
colleagues better and that might create
a community that is kind of mutually
supportive in a way that we not so much
cluttered by by knowledge and red tape
but we can actually allow ourselves to
activate our natural capacity to care
and and our like to to to allow
ourselves to be authentic in our natural
state of being and connected that level
yeah it mean it's interesting when
you're talking about the group care
between doctors colleagues when when
someone that we know commits suicide
it's such an important inquiry
especially if we didn't know they were
close it's an important inquiry to
recognize that you actually don't know
how close anyone you're talking to ever
is to committing suicide mm-hmm and you
don't know how close to threshold they
are and how your interaction is going to
affect their relationship to that
threshold and simply being aware of that
changes the importance you put on how
you show up in all the interactions so
much well we've come a long way in
looking at taking a big circle
starting in what does it what does heart
based medicine mean to you and we're
ending on a note of how important it is
to develop a sensitivity for each other
and to be present with each other and to
know and how in how many ways this this
finds reflections in our diagnostic
capacity in the way with device
treatments in a way we want to create a
health care system that overcomes the
many limitations that that we're facing
at the moment towards a system where
people will feel singing with her as
human beings rather than being seen as a
disease with with some kind of
background that clearly doesn't is it so
important for us yeah thank you thank
you for taking your time David thanks
for having me thanks for following the
call to help this movement birth
this has been a heart based medicine
production thanks for listening